Abby Morton Diaz Papers, 1879-1900
Sophia Smith Collection
Abby Morton Diaz papers
1879-1900
Diaz, Abby Morton, 1821-1904
MS 48
1 box (.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Author, Suffragist, Social reformer. The Abby Morton Diaz Papers include biographical articles; articles and pamphlets written by Diaz; photographs; suffrage leaflets; reports of the Women's Educational and Industrial Union; miscellaneous pamphlets; and a book that includes a speech by Diaz.
Abby Morton Diaz (1821-1904) was born in Plymouth, Massachusetts. Her father, Ichabod Morton, was a social reformer involved in anti-slavery, temperance, and (with Horace Mann) education movements. Abby was secretary for the Juvenile Anti-Slavery Society as a girl. Her family moved to the Brook Farm Community in 1842, where Abby stayed to teach until 1847. She married Manuel Diaz, a Cuban, in 1845. They later separated. Abby taught singing and opened a dancing school in Plymouth. She published her first story in Atlantic Monthly in 1861 and thereafter published juvenile stories and articles on "domestic culture," social reform for women, religious freedom, transcendentalism, and in later years, Christian Science. A children's book, The William Henry Letters, was published in 1870. Abby was one of the original board members of the Women's Education and Industrial Union of Boston (1877) and served as its president, 1881-92, and vice president, 1892-1902. After 1902, she was the honorary president. She traveled and lectured throughout the U.S., and eventually became active in the suffrage movement.
The Abby Morton Diaz Papers include biographical articles, articles and pamphlets written by Diaz, photographs, suffrage leaflets, reports of the Women's Educational and Industrial Union, miscellaneous pamphlets, and a book that includes a speech by Diaz.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES
III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Ralph Morton Diaz, grandson of Abby Morton Diaz, donated the Diaz Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1953.
Anti-slavery movements--United States-History--Sources; Abolitionists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women--Suffrage--United States--History--Sources; Diaz, Abby Morton, 1821-1904; Women's Educational and Industrial Union (Boston, Mass.); Social reformers--Massachusetts--Biography--Sources; Authors, American--19th century--Biography--Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles about Diaz, 1883-1904, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph (photostat), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- SERIES II. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES
  - Pamphlets and articles, 1879-99, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speech by Diaz in Old Anti-Slavery Days. Proceedings of the Commemorative Meeting, Held by the Danvers Historical Society, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Publishers' circulars, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writings by others
    - Old South Leaflets, Fourth Series, 1886 (by Patrick Henry, Thomas Paine, and others from the American Revolution era) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets and articles, 1871, 1886, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Suffrage leaflets, 1888-1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Women's Educational and Industrial Union: reports, 1887, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)